Data scientist with 13 years experience in analyzing heterogeneous data, designing machine learning pipelines, and general software development. Developed packages in R and Python, published 15+ peer-reviewed articles, and designed data science courses using novel pedagogies. I value collaboration above all else, which is why I enjoy building tools and teaching skills that empower teams to access and understand their data.

Education

Stanford University Pacific Grove, CA

PHD IN BIOLOGY 2022

• Advised by Jeremy Goldbogen

· Dissertation: Baleen whale physiology revealed through the integration of bio-logging and ecoinformatics

San Francisco State University San Francisco, CA

MS in Geographic Information Systems

2018

- Advised by Ellen Hines
- · Thesis: Using energy landscapes to understand seabird movement and spatial ecology
- Graduate hood, College of Science & Engineering

Columbia University New York, NY

BS IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Publications

Field measurements reveal the risk of microplastic ingestion by filter-feeding megafauna

KAHANE-RAPPORT, S.R., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., FAHLBUSCH, J.A., FRIEDLAENDER, A.S., CALAMBOKIDIS, J., ..., SAVOCA, M.S.

Fast and furious: energetic tradeoffs and scaling of high-speed foraging in rorqual Integrative Organismal Biology

GOUGH, W.T., CADE, D.E., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., POTVIN, J., FISH, F.E., ..., GOLDBOGEN, J.A.

Blue whales increase feeding rates at fine-scale ocean features Fahlbusch, J.A., Czapanskiy, M.F., Calambokidis, J., Cade, D.E., Abrahms, B., ..., Goldbogen, J.A.

Baleen whale inhalation variability revealed using animal-borne video tags

Nazario, E.C., Cade, D.E., Bierlich, K., Czapanskiy, M.F., Goldbogen, J.A., ..., Friedlaender, A.S.

How reproducibility will accelerate discovery through collaboration in physio-logging

CZAPANSKIY, M.F., BELTRAN, R.S.

An accelerometer-derived ballistocardiogram method for detecting heartrates in free-ranging marine mammals

CZAPANSKIY, M.F., PONGANIS, P.J., FAHLBUSCH, J.A., SCHMITT, T.L., GOLDBOGEN, J.A.

Elephant seals time their long-distance migrations using a map sense

BELTRAN, R.S., YUEN, A.L., CONDIT, R., ROBINSON, P.W., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., ..., COSTA, D.P.

Scaling of maneuvering performance in baleen whales: larger whales outperform expectations

SEGRE, P.S., GOUGH, W.T., ROUALDES, E.A., CADE, D.E., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., ..., GOLDBOGEN, J.A.

Tools for integrating inertial sensor data with video bio-loggers, including estimation of animal orientation, motion, and position

CADE, D.E., GOUGH, W.T., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., FAHLBUSCH, J.A., KAHANE-RAPPORT, S.R., ..., GOLDBOGEN, J.A.

Baleen whale prey consumption based on high-resolution foraging measurements

SAVOCA, M.S., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., KAHANE-RAPPORT, S.R., GOUGH, W.T., FAHLBUSCH, J.A., ..., GOLDBOGEN, J.A.

Modelling short-term energetic costs of sonar disturbance to cetaceans using high-resolution foraging data

CZAPANSKIY, M.F., SAVOCA, M.S., GOUGH, W.T., SEGRE, P.S., WISNIEWSKA, D.M., ..., GOLDBOGEN, J.A.

Nature Communications

2022

Proceedings of the Royal Society B

2022

Peer.I

Frontiers in Physiology

Journal of Exp. Bio.

2022

Current Biology

2022

Journal of Exp. Bio.

2022

Animal Biotelemetry

Nature 2021

Journal of Applied Ecology

2021

Scaling of oscillatory kinematics and Froude efficiency in baleen whales

Gough, W.T., Smith, H.J., Savoca, M.S., Czapanskiy, M.F., Fish, F.E., ..., Goldbogen, J.A.

Journal of Exp. Bio.

2021

Cervical air sac oxygen profiles in diving emperor penguins: parabronchial ventilation and the respiratory oxygen store

Journal of Exp. Bio.

WILLIAMS, C.L., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., JOHN, J.S., ST LEGER, J., SCADENG, M., PONGANIS, P.J.

Why whales are big but not bigger: Physiological drivers and ecological limits in the age of ocean giants

Science

GOLDBOGEN, J.A., CADE, D.E., WISNIEWSKA, D.M., POTVIN, J., ..., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., ..., PYENSON, N.D.

GOLDBOGEN, J.A., CADE, D.E., CALAMBOKIDIS, J., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., FAHLBUSCH, J., ..., PONGANIS, P.J.

2019

Extreme bradycardia and tachycardia in the world's largest animal

PNAS 2019

Diving behavior of Pink-footed Shearwaters Ardenna creatopus rearing chicks on Isla Mocha, Chile

Marine Ornithology

ADAMS, J., FELIS, J.J., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., CARLE, R., HODUM, P.

2019

Collision and displacement vulnerability to offshore wind energy infrastructure among marine birds of the Pacific Outer Continental Shelf

Journal of Env. Mgmt.

KELSEY, E.C., FELIS, J.J., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., PEREKSTA, D.M., ADAMS, J.

2018

IN REVIEW

rstickleback: supervised behavior detection in bio-logging data

Journal of Open Source Software

CZAPANSKIY, M.F., MANN, A.

TECHNICAL REPORTS

Habitat Affinities and At-Sea Ranging Behaviors among Main Hawaiian Island Seabirds: Breeding Seabird Telemetry, 2013-2016.

OCS Study BOEM 2020-006.

ADAMS, J., FELIS, J.J., CZAPANSKIY, M.F.

2020

Trends in mammalian predator control trapping events intended to protect ground-nesting, endangered birds at Haleakalā National Park, Hawaiʻi: 2000–14. U.S. Geological Survey Open-File

Report 2019-1122.

KELSEY, E.C., ADAMS, J., CZAPANSKIY, M.F., FELIS, J.J., YEE, J.L., KAHOLOAA R.L., AND BAILEY, C.N.

2019

Teaching and Mentoring

Undergraduate researcher mentor

Stanford University

RFFFS MENTOR

- Mentored Lilah McCormick in quantitative ecophysiology.
- · Lilah learned reproducible research techniques in R and is writing a paper about measuring cardiac function in narwhals.

Just Enough Software Engineering (For Scientists)

Stanford University

LEAD INSTRUCTOR AND COURSE DESIGNER

- · Self-guided, mastery-based software engineering course for biosciences graduate students
- · Two-week intensive short course

Introduction to Physiological Ecology

Undergraduate researcher mentor

Stanford University

TEACHING ASSISTANT

NSF REU MENTOR

CSU Monterey Bay REU

· Mentored Hayden Smith in quantitative analysis.

· Hayden presented his work at the 2020 Society for Int. and Comp. Bio. Meeting and published it in the Journal of Exp. Bio. (Gough et al., 2021).

The Carpentries

Data Carpentry CERTIFIED INSTRUCTOR

2018 - present

Introduction to Ecology

Stanford University

San Francisco State University

Introduction to GIS

TEACHING ASSISTANT 2016 - 2017

Software

TEACHING ASSITANT

| A MACHINE LEARNING PIPELINE FOR DETECTING FINE-SCALE BEHAVIORAL EVENTS IN BIO-LOGGING DATA | Python | |
|--|--------|--|
| rstickleback (github.com/FlukeAndFeather/rstickleback) | | |
| An R interface to the stickleback machine learning pipeline | R | |
| catsr (doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5140484) | | |
| Tools for reading and visualizing 3D bio-logging data; accompanies Cade et al. (2021) | R | |
| beats (github.com/FlukeAndFeather/beats) | | |
| Interactive tools for importing, annotating, and validating ECG bio-logger data | R | |

Conference presentations

Stickleback: A machine learning pipeline for detecting behavioral events in bio-logging data 7TH INTERNATIONAL BIO-LOGGING SYMPOSIUM Quantifying the Influence of Energy Windscapes on Seabird Distributions OCEAN SCIENCES MEETING Modeling Seabird Habitat Accessibility Society For Conservation GIS Annual Conference Taking the Plunge: Comparing Diving Behavior of Red-footed and Brown Boobies Breeding on Lehua Islet, Hawaii

Work experience _____

PACIFIC SEABIRD GROUP ANNUAL MEETING

| U.S. Geological Survey Western Ecological Research Center | |
|---|-------------|
| BIOLOGICAL SCIENCES TECHNICIAN | 2014 - 2017 |
| University of Montana Avian Science Center | |
| Avian Point Count Technician | 2014 |
| Friends of Cooper Island | |
| FIELD ASSISTANT AND DATA ANALYST | 2012 - 2013 |
| Point Blue Conservation Science | |
| Marine Ecology Intern | 2013 |
| Microsoft | |
| SOFTWARE DEVELOPER ENGINEER IN TEST | 2009 - 2013 |

Awards and scholarships _____

- Stanford Data Science Scholar Fellowship, Stanford Data Science Initiative (2020)
- Stanford Graduate Fellowship, Vice Provost for Graduate Education (2018)
- Graduate Hood, San Francisco State University, College of Science and Engineering (2018)
- Esri Development Center Student of the Year, Esri (2018)
- COAST Research Award, California State University, Council on Ocean Affairs (2018)
- Maxwell Memorial Scholarship, San Francisco State University, College of Science and Engineering (2017)
- Pease Award, San Francisco State University, Department of Geography and Environment (2017)
- CWEP Award for Graduate Student Writing, San Francisco State University (2017)

2016